この三人があの未完成のフィルムの殺人事件について
推理しています
彼らの話をそれぞれ聞いてぜひお判断してください
はい
お前らが
ミステリーに詳しいってのは
彼が中城順哉です
撮影班で助監督
こちらが羽場智博
小道具班です
よろしく
そしてこちらが
チャオ
注：义大利语的招呼语 相当于中文的"你好"、"再见"
沢木口美崎　広報班です
遠路はるばる　ご苦労さま　よろしくね
あっ　はい
大丈夫なの　こんな面子で
退屈な窓辺に吹き込む風に
顔を顰めたのは照れくさ　その裏返し
KamiGami
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
曖昧に頷く掌の今日
描いてる自分は少し大袈裟で
何かが変わりそうな気がしているよ
心に呼びかける君のせいだね
曇り空覗いた予感
This is a work of fiction.
Any resemblance to real persons, groups or events are purely coincidental.
手を伸ばそう　いつよりも力強い勇気で
These three people have theories about the movie's unsolved murder mystery.
Hyouka
Please listen to their ideas and tell us what you think.
光も影もまだ遠くで
Okay!
So you guys
それでも僕らは優しさの理由が知りたい
are the mystery masters?
This is Nakajou Jun'ya, the vice-director from the filming team.
今は誰の名前でもない
This is Haba Tomohiro from the prop team.
Hello.
輝きの彼方へ
And this is...
Ciao!
Sawakiguchi Misaki from the marketing team.
全部過去になる前に見つけに行こう
Thanks for coming all the way here!
Nice to meetcha!
S-Sure!
Is she taking this seriously at all?
Well then, we'll leave this in your hands.
では　よろしくお願いします
Come get us later, 'kay?
後で呼んでね
古丘废村杀人事件
ごゆっくり
Take your time.
Sorry fer gettin' ya mixed up in this mess.
厄介な話を持ち込んで　すまんなあ
ノリで始めた話でも落ちがつかんと寒いからな
We mighta started on a whim but it'd be a shame if we couldn't finish it, y'know?
ま　ちょっと手伝ってくれよ
Hope ya'll help us a bit.
Yeah...
Oh, right...
そうでした
これ　皆さんで食べてください
Please, help yourselves.
These are whisky candies, right?
これ　ウイスキーボンボンだよね
新製品の試供品なんだそうです
It's a sample of a new product.
They're strong!
きつっ
Well, should we start?
じゃ　始めるか
You're on the filming team, right?
中城先輩は撮影班でしたよね
撮影は大変でしたか
Did you have a hard time with the shooting?
演技や演出はアドリブ利かせて楽しくやれたが
The actors had a fun time improvisin'...
Murder in the Ghost Town of Furuoka
Gettin' there was a job and a half, though.
大変だったのは移動だな
電車とバスで一時間はかかる
Took over an hour by bus 'n' train.
Why'd it hafta be in the middle o' nowhere?
何であんなところをロケ地に選らんだのやら
何でだったんですか
Why was it?
It caught a few people's fancy 'cos it looked interestin'.
見た目が面白い場所ってことで推したやつがいるんだよ
Narakubo is basically a ghost town, right? How'd you get in?
楢窪地区は廃村だって聞きましたが
よく立ち入りできましたね
What's-her-face talked to the caretaker 'bout it.
そいつが管理人に話をつけてくれたんだ
それが何が関係あるのか
Is that important?
Thank you, that's all I needed.
ありがとうございます
勉強になりました
Please go on.
続きをどうぞ
How is Hongou, the scriptwriter?
あの　脚本の本郷さんの容態はどうですか
あんまりよくないみたいだな
Not doin' so well.
ま　あいつを責めるわけにもいかんだろが
Not that anyone blames her or anythin'.
Was she particularly frail?
本郷さんはあまり丈夫な方じゃなかったんですか
Yeah. She missed school a bunch of times and didn't come to the shootings either.
そうだな
学校を休むことも何度があったし
撮影にも出てこなかったし
I guess she was working on the script.
脚本の執筆に苦しんでて出られなかったんじゃん
Did the team not like Hongou's script?
本郷先輩の脚本は評判悪かったんですか
誰もけちをつけたりしなかった
No one complained! Not a bad word was said 'bout it!
あいつを責めたことなんかなかったぞ
ということは　内心はそうしたかった
So the people in charge wanted to do it?
何が言いたいんだ
Whatcha gettin' at? We all approved of Hongou's work!
本郷の仕事は全員が認めてたさ
'Course I did too!
もちろん俺もだ
By the way...
それでですね　先輩
Did Hongou tell you anything about who the culprit might be?
本郷さんから誰が犯人役か聞いてませんでしたか
俺が知る限りじゃ
Not as far as I know...
Wait a sec.
おや　待ってよ
Kounosu told us to do our best.
そう言えば　鴻巣に頑張れとかなんとか言ってたような
これくらいは誰にでも言いそうだ
Anyone would say that.
And did you ask the actors?
じゃ　役者の人に聞きましたか
Has anyone heard anything relevant?
誰かそういう話を受けてないか
Nope, no one.
いや　誰も
Do you know if the twist was something physical? Or a trick of the mind?
物理的なトリックなのか心理的なトリックなのかは
What's the difference?
どう違うんだ
No more questions?
ほかに質問はないか
じゃ　俺の考えを聞いてもらおうか
Then how 'bout listenin' to my idea?
お願いします
Please.
If ya ask me, a script don't need no twist.
俺に言わせりゃ
普通の客はトリックなんか気にしないさ
盛り上がればいいんだ
It's all 'bout the excitement!
犯人はお前だ
You're the culprit!
Just solve the case somehow,
って決めつけて
and watch the culprit confess, cryin' like a baby.
犯人が涙ながらに事情を語る
これさえあったきゃ文句はないだろ
That oughta do it.
Fin
Kaitou's death was pretty excitin', right?
そういう盛り上げって言えば
海藤の死ぬところはよかったな
A rip-roarin' death for the proud leader o' the prop team.
小道具班ご自慢の演出で派手に死んでくれた
Real nice, huh?
あれはいい
あのシーンはアドリブだったと
You improvised that scene?
Yeah. They're all so obsessed with that crap,
どいつもこいつもこだわり過ぎなんだよ
the rules of mystery or whatever. Drama's where it's at!
ミステリーの作法やらなんやら
そんな細かい話より
ドラマだよ
タイトルもストレート
Plus, the title's gotta lay it bare.
"Murder in the Ghost Town of Furuoka."
古丘廃村殺人事件
Murder in the
Ghost Town
of Furuoka
...or somethin' like that, so folks come 'n' see it.
とかにして　客を呼べるようにしないと
本郷だってそのあたりのことが分かってたぜ
Hongou must've known that too.
So then, what's your theory?
それで　中城先輩のお考えは
あの死に方は要するにあれだろ
The way he died, what was it...
A locked room murder.
密室ってやつだ
Kaitou died in a room with all exits locked.
ほかに出口のない部屋で海藤が死んでた
さて　犯人はどうやって殺したんでしょう
So how'd the culprit kill him? Or rather...
ってのが問題だ
How'd he get out?
Yeah, how?
では　どうやって
Piece o' cake! The window!
簡単さ　窓だよ
The window?
窓
Yeah! The culprit escaped through the window after killin' Kaitou, clear as day!
犯人は海藤を殺したあと
窓から出ていたに決まってるじゃないか
The window? Sorry, my memory's a bit hazy.
窓
どうも記憶が曖昧なんですが
Satoshi, got the floor plan?
里志　見取り図は
イエス、サー
Yessir!
ちょっと待ってて
Just a sec.
Here you go.
はい　お待たせ
Kaitou died here, in the stage's left wing.
海藤が死んでいたのはここ
上手袖だね
The other characters entered here, from the right corridor.
ほかの登場人物は右通路からここに入った
その前に　この扉に鍵がかかってたから
The door was locked, so someone had to go get the master key.
誰かがマスター鍵を取りに戻ったよね
And when they entered the left wing, Kaitou was lying there dead.
それで　上手袖に戻ると海藤が死んでたと
The doors to the stage and the crossover were blocked by junk, right?
舞台と舞台裏の通路は荷物やがらくたで塞がれてたわよね
Then the only possible exits were these:
そうなると
殺害現場へのアクセスは　この二か所だけになるわけだね
The door they came in by and the left wing's window.
皆が入った扉と上手袖の窓
But did Hongou know that as well?
あの　そういった事実は本郷さんも知っていたんですか
えっと　あの
Yeah, that's an important point.
確かにそれは重要だね
What do you mean?
どういうこと
本郷さんが現場の状態を知らずに
If Hongou wrote the script just based on the floor plan, without seeing the place for herself,
見取り図だけをもとに脚本を書いていたら
then she might've intended the murderer to take another route.
別のルートを考えていた可能性もあるからね
Don't worry 'bout that. Before she wrote the script, she surveyed the location once herself.
それはない
本郷も脚本を書く前に　一度下見に行ったみたいだ
When was that?
それはいつ頃ですか
六月
In June... or was it the end of May?
いや　五月の終わりごろかな
Anyway, that window's how the culprit came and went.
つまり　だ
犯人は窓から出入りしたんだよ
And there ya have it. That's how Kaitou died.
こうすれば　ドーアを通らずに
海藤を殺すシーンが撮れるだろ
どうだ
Howzat?!
How should I know?
どうだと言われても
Wouldn't that be a pretty boring mystery?
でもそれはちょっとミステリーとして出来が悪すぎます
Tell Hongou 'bout that.
それは本郷に言ってくれよ
あいつもミステリーに詳しいわけじゃなかった
Not like she knows anythin' 'bout mysteries either.
Doubt she woulda come up with some cool twist.
立派なトリックが用意できなかったんだろ
だとしても犯人は
But then who was the murderer?
犯人
The murderer?
What if the murderer's identity is the twist? Who could it be?
仮にそれがトリックだとして
犯人は誰になるのかってことです
And after everyone entered the room,
それに　現場に全員が踏み込んだ後
その窓の外が映されたじゃないですか
wasn't there a shot showing what was outside the window?
Yeah.
あれを見れば
It was clear that no one left through the window.
窓の外に人が通った跡がないことははっきりしています
If anyone had walked through that sea of grass, it'd be bent out of the way.
あの草の生い茂る中を人が通ったら　必ず痕跡が残ります
でもそんな描写一切ない
There was no such evidence.
There's no way they could have escaped through the window!
窓から逃げるという方法は無理です
Hongou might've just forgotten 'bout it.
本郷が書き忘れたのかもしれない
The moment you use that argument it's all over.
それを言ったら　おしまいです
それに本郷先輩のシナリオはすべてつじつまがあっていると聞いています
Besides, I heard that Hongou paid great attention to realism.
But then...
だとしたら
Got it!
そうだ　夏草だ
Fresh grass!
Like I said, Hongou went there 'round the end of May!
さっき言ったよな
本郷が現場の下見にきたのは五月末だって
その頃はまだ夏草は茂ってなかったんだ
The grass must've grown out after that!
That's why she thought the window'd work!
だから本郷は窓を使えると思いこんだんだよ
But then we just gotta cut the grass
だったら　次の撮影の時に夏草を刈り込んで
and retake from the corpse scene at the next shooting, and it'll all match up!
死体のシーンから撮り直せばつじつまが合うじゃないか
See?! Howzat?!
ほら見ろう　どうだ
All right, that settles it!
よーし　これで解決だ
犯人は窓から逃げた
The culprit escaped through the window! It works!
これでできるぞ
やれる
Hell yeah!
Catch ya later!
じゃ　頼んだぞ
Could that really be it? That's not much of a twist.
あんなんでいいの
トリックとも呼べないじゃない
At least it's physically possible, though.
でもまあ
物理的には実行可能だしね
そうだけど
Yeah, but still...
Oreki...
折木さん
Do you think Nakajou's theory was what Hongou really intended?
今の中城さんのお話が本郷さんの本意だったと思いますか
You don't like it?
気に入らないのか
いいえ　そんな
No, I just...
I have some trouble accepting it.
ただちょっと納得できなくて
So you don't like it.
要するに気に入らないだろ
You're right in that Nakajou's theory is contradictory.
まあ　中城の話に矛盾があるのは確かだが
What? There's a contradiction?
えっ何何　矛盾あるの
It's a simple resolution, but it flies in the face of common sense.
ごく簡単な物理的解決は　ごく簡単な心理的側面から否定されるってことだ
うん　どういうこと
What do you mean?
That's a roundabout way to put it, Houtarou.
回りくどい言い方だね　奉太郎
Fitting for the detective, I guess.
実に探偵役らしいよ
Um,
あの　つまりはどういうことなのでしょうか
what exactly do you mean?
Put yourself in the culprit's shoes. There's no way he'd enter through the window.
犯人の気持ちになってみれば
とても窓からなんて入れないってことだよ
If he entered through the window, he'd risk crossing someone's line of sight.
この窓から侵入するには
必ず誰かの視界を通るリスクがあるだろう
ほら　こっちもこっちも
Here, or here.
外を歩いてたら必ず誰かに目撃される
If he entered from outside the building then someone would see him for sure,
especially during broad daylight.
しかも真昼間だぞ
I see.
なるほど
If I were the culprit, I wouldn't have gone in that way.
もし僕が犯人だったら　こんなルートはまず取れない
That's the long and short of it.
まあ　そういうことだ
But we don't know if Hongou thought the same way.
でも　本郷先輩がそこに気づいてたかどうかは
分かんないよね
That's true.
そうだな
However, if we can read Hongou's script, we can find that out.
だが本郷の書いた脚本を読めばそのあたりも分かると思うぞ
By the way, have you guys read much crime fiction?
ところで　皆
探偵小説はどれぐらい読んでるのかな
Why?
何で
I realized while listening to Nakajou
さっき中城先輩の話を聞いていて思ったんだ
that everyone has their own idea of what a "mystery novel" is.
一口に推理ものと言っても捕らえ方が違うぞってね
His way of thinking certainly was novel.
まあ　確かに中城の考え方はある意味斬新だったな
うん　奉太郎はどう
How about you, Houtarou?
あまり
Not a lot. Read a few, that's all.
文庫いくつかくらいだな
Mayaka?
摩耶花は
The usual. Agatha Christie and such.
普通
クリスティーとか
Good start.
王道だね
And you, Chitanda?
千反田さんは
I haven't read any.
読みません
Not a single one? At all?
まったく　ぜんぜん
I don't really enjoy mysteries...
私はあまりミステリーを楽しめないのかもしれない
I've tried enough to realize that.
と思うぐらいまでは読みました
I haven't read any for years, though.
ここ何年間は全く触れてないです
それは意外だね
I didn't expect that.
そういうお前はどうなんだ
And what about you?
Me? Well...
僕　僕は
I know.
私　知ってるわよ
福ちゃんはシャーロッキアンに憧れてるのよね
Fuku is trying to be a real Sherlockian.
何ですか　シャ―ロッキアンって
What's a Sherlockian?
I guess that refers to Sherlock Holmes' enthusiastic fans.
シャ―ロク·ホームズの熱心なファンのことだろ
Really, really enthusiastic fans.
とってっも熱心なファン　よね
Right?
"Sherlockian" means something a bit different...
シャ―ロッキアンっていうのはそういうのともちょっと違うんだけど
What did you think?
どうでしたか
Um...
ええと
We've refuted Nakajou's theory.
中城先輩の案は却下です
I see.
そうですか
Oh, and also...
ああ　それと
What?
何が
Can we see the script? We'd like to know how much detail Hongou put in it.
脚本が手に入りませんか
本郷の注意力を知りたいというが
Okay. I'll go to look for it. In the meantime, please talk to Haba Tomohiro from the prop team.
分かりました
探しておきますので
それまで彼と話しておいてください
小道具班の羽場智博です
Hi there.
よっ　君らミステリーの話ができるんだってね
I hear you chaps might be up for a little tête-à-tête regarding mysteries.
处暑
暑将退
伏而潜处 故名也
Limit of Heat
As the Sun's strength falters,
summer's feverish heat breaks for the first time.
Hyouka
If one considers mysteries to be a duel between the writer and the reader,
ま　ミステリーを作家と読者の勝負と考えるなら
アマチュアの本郷が相手じゃ　ちょっと物足りないけどな
a mere dilettante such as Hongou barely counts as an opponent.
Yeah, we heard she wasn't familiar with mysteries.
本郷さんはミステリーに詳しくなかったそうですね
Indeed.
Those books were her crash course into that enigmatic realm.
あれが本郷の一夜漬けの教材だ
Prior to this film, she knew nothing about mystery, not even via graphic novels or cinema.
この撮影を始めれまでは
小説どころか　漫画や映画でもミステリーに触れたことがなかったそうだ
Ah, it's Nobuhara's translation! A new edition as well!
延原訳だ
The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes
Conan Doyle / Translated by Nobuhara Ken
それも新装版
She tried learning about mystery through Holmes?
ホームズでミステリーを勉強しようとしてたんですか
Precisely! What a total amateur, I say!
そうなんだ
だから素人だっていうんだよ
そうとも言えるでしょうね
I wonder about that.
Oreki, Oreki!
折木さん　折木さん
What?
どうした
変わった印がしてあります　ほら
There's some weird code here! Look!
The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes
Conan Doyle
A Scandal in Bohemia
The Red-Headed League
A Case of Identity
The Boscombe Valley Mystery
The Five Orange Pips
The Man with the Twisted Lip
The Blue Carbuncle
The Speckled Band
A Case of Identity
The Copper Beeches
Look, here too!
ほらほら　こちらのにも
The Case-Book of Sherlock Holmes
Conan Doyle
The Illustrious Client
The Blanched Soldier
The Mazarin Stone
The Three Gables
The Sussex Vampire
The Three Garridebs
The Problem of Thor Bridge
The Creeping Man
The Lion's Mane
The Veiled Lodger
She probably just marked off the ideas she could use.
使えるネタに丸をつけただけだろ
I see.
そうですか
Putting that aside,
それより　推理を始めようじゃないか
why don't we get down to brass tacks?
Is that the floor plan?
この見取り図は
I've marked the characters as such.
2nd floor
Sound
control room
Senoue
Wellhole
Dimmer
room
Utility
Sugimura
Stairwell
Kounosu
West
1st floor
Right wing
Stage
Left wing
Kaitou
Storage
room
Katsuta
Toilet
Waiting
room
Yamanishi
Office
Reception
Waiting
room
Toilet
Entrance lobby
Hall
町役場で入手した
Then please tell us your theory.
では　聞かせてください
By my assessment, this mystery is not difficult at all.
僕の考えじゃ　あのミステリーはさほど難しくない
In fact, it's really quite simple.
むしろ簡単な部類に入るね
How so?
というと？
This murder wasn't planned in advance.
あの殺人は計画的なものじゃないってことだ
Rather, the culprit merely struck when the time was right.
むしろ犯人はたまたま条件が整ったから　それに乗じて犯行に及んだ
Why?
なぜですか
Had it been planned, how would he relocate Kaitou to the left wing?
もし計画的なら　どうやって海藤を上手袖に誘導したんだ？
海藤が一人で劇場一階の右側に向かったのは
Kaitou proceeded alone to the right side of the theater after choosing that key himself.
あいつが自発的に鍵を選んだ結果だ
Furthermore, this was a locked room murder.
さて　これは密室殺人だ
All possible escape routes were secured and the only one left viable, the window,
逃げ道はどれも塞がっていて
唯一のルートである窓の外には足跡などは残されていない
showed no signs of use.
つまり　海藤を殺した犯人は普通には逃げられなかった
To wit: Kaitou's murderer could not escape via any normal means.
As for whether he could have simply taken and returned the master key...
では犯人がマスターキーを利用して現場に侵入
その後で鍵を戻した可能性はないか
A conclusion as vapid as it is fallacious.
これはつまらないし　成立もしない
To retrieve the master key from the office, one would need to cross the entrance lobby.
鍵がある事務室に入るには　玄関ロビーを必ず通らないといけない
Any one of the characters could easily witness someone doing so.
玄関ロビーはどの人物からも目撃される危険が常にあった
Thus, not one of them could safely enter the office.
だから　どの人物も事務室には安全に入れない
And not just the office, either.
安全に入れないのは事務室だけじゃなかった
The entire right-hand corridor that leads to the left wing was accessible by none.
上手袖に続く　一階右側の通路そのものが
誰にも侵入できない場所だったってことになる
ここが重要だ　なぜか
Ergo, this area is vital.
And why is that?
Because it means the culprit couldn't have approached the locked room.
トリックを仕掛けるために　密室に近づくことさえできないってことですね
Well... Essentially, yes.
まあ　その通りだ
同じ理由で　被害者本人が密室を作った可能性も否定される
Likewise, the victim himself could not have locked the room.
What else is there?
他の可能性
Nor could he have been murdered through mechanical means, or after the door had been opened.
機会仕掛けの殺人や早業殺人も不可能だ
He was quite clearly dead, with his arm severed from his body.
腕が落ちるほどの斬撃を受けて死んでるんだから
Thus, the solution to Hongou's locked room mystery is something other than the obvious.
要するに　本郷が作ったこの密室
正面から突破するのはなかなか難しい
What do you think? You're Oreki, right?
どうだ？　キミ折木君だったかな
How would you solve this locked room mystery?
この密室どう解けばいいと思う？
Yeah, I dunno.
さあ　わかりません
だめだなあ　そんなことじゃ
Oh please, that simply won't do!
いや　でも無理もないかな
これが鍵だ
But I can't say I'm all that surprised.
ザイルが？
This is the key.
I'm on the prop team, as you know.
僕は小道具班だ　本郷から念を押されてね
Hongou instructed us to procure a rope that wouldn't snap under a person's weight.
「人がぶら下っても絶対に切れないロープを用意しよ」って
Do you understand its purpose?
使い方はもうわかるだろう
だからさ　一階から入れないなら　二階から入ればいいんだよ
It's like I always say,
if you can't enter via the first floor, try the second!
Kounosu was there on the second floor's right-hand corridor.
二階の右側通路には鴻巣がいた
Though she may seem delicate to you, she is in fact in the Mountaineering Club.
実は鴻巣は華奢に見えるが　あれで登山部なんだ
She lowered the rope from the second floor,
鴻巣は二階の窓からザイルを垂らし
それをつたって上手袖で海藤を殺し　帰りも同じルートで逃走した
slew Kaitou from where he stood in the left wing,
and used that very same means of escape.
Were I to select a title for the movie, I'd call it...
あの映画にタイトルをつけるなら　そうだな
「不可視の進入」とでもつけるかな
"Invisible Entrance", or something like that.
And now, your opinions please.
さあ　次は君らの意見を聞こうか
Did Hongou ask you for anything besides the rope?
ザイルのほかに　本郷先輩から何か注文はありましたか
特にはないが
Not really. But she didn't always order everything she required.
本郷はむらっ気があったんだろうな
For instance, the volume of blood she had us prepare was not nearly enough,
たとえば　指示されてた血糊の量も全然足りなくてねえ
仕方がないから　こちらが気をきかせて大量に用意したよ
so we had to go to some lengths to make more.
他に何か？　ないなら…
Anything else? If that is all...
あのう
Um...
What?
何だ？
たいしたことじゃないんですが　出来てる映像を見ましたか
Just wondering,
have you seen what's done of the movie?
実はまだ見てないんだ
I confess that I have not.
なんか腹立つ
He pisses me off!
How so?
何が？
His attitude! Were you okay with that?
あの態度よ　福ちゃんなんとも思わなかったの
ホームズまで馬鹿にされて
He even made fun of Holmes!
Not really.
べつに
Why?!
どうして
Well, Holmes is aimed at beginners.
ホームズが初心者向けだってのは　一面の真実だよ
確かに本郷先輩は初心者だったみたいだね
And it does seem like Hongou is a beginner.
で　どうだ？　羽場案は
Well...
So what do you think of Haba's theory?
まあ　いいんじゃないのかな
I guess it sort of works.
It's not a very interesting twist, but Hongou ordering that rope is pretty decisive.
つまらない結論だけど
本郷先輩がロープを用意するように言ったのは決定的だよ
I don't have a problem with it either.
私も問題ないと思うわ
I...
私は　私は賛成できないです
I can't accept that theory.
Like with Nakajou's, something just feels off about it.
先の中城さんの案もそうでしたが
何か違和感のようなものを感じます
I don't really know why, but I doubt Hongou was planning something like that.
よくわからないんですが　本郷さんの真意はそこにはないんじゃないかと
Haven't you had enough of those?
その辺でやめとけよ
Huh? When did I have that many?
あら　こんなに食べていましたか
なんだか変わったお味で　こういうものなのか気になったものですから
They tasted so interesting, I couldn't stop thinking about it.
ちぃちゃん　大丈夫？
Chi, are you all right?
大丈夫ですよ　大丈夫
I'm all right! All right!
折木さんは　あれが正しいと思われますか
Oreki, do you think his theory is correct?
思わない
I don't.
Why?
なんでよ
If we were talking about a real murder, it might work,
もしあれが実際の人殺しだったら使えるかもしれないが
The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes
Conan Doyle / Translated by Nobuhara Ken
but it can't have been used in this movie.
あの映画の中では使えない
つまり？
Meaning?
It's at odds with the video.
映像との矛盾だよ
Oh, I see. The window, right?
ああ　そうか　あの窓は
It hadn't been touched for years, and didn't fit properly.
長年放置されて　建てつけが悪くなっていた
It took Katsuta some real effort just to get it open.
勝田が揺すってもなかなか開かなかったし　相当固かったはずだ
It creaked quite badly, not to mention it opens upward.
軋む音も大きい　しかも上向きだ
It'd be almost impossible to quietly open a window like that while hanging on a rope.
そんな窓をザイルでぶら下って静かにあけるなんてさすがに無理だ
大体そんな窓をガタガタやってる間
And would Kaitou just stand by and watch while she rattled away at the window?
部屋の中の海藤は突っ立てるのか
間抜けすぎるね
He wouldn't be that stupid.
So that's why you asked him if he'd seen the movie?
だから　さっき羽場にビデオ見たか聞いてたのね
Hongou surveyed the theater.
本郷はあの劇場を下調べしていた
あの窓が重大なトリックなら　開くかどうかチェックしたはずだ
If the window was a key part of the plot, she would've checked that as well.
だが　実際に撮られたのはああいう映像だろ
But this wasn't reflected in the video,
so we can conclude that Hongou didn't care about the window.
つまり本郷は窓の状態なんか気にしてなかったんだ
うかつに賛成なんてするんじゃなかったわ
I shouldn't have just said yes without thinking!
How was it?
いかがでしたか
却下です
No good.
そうですか
I see.
I've brought you the script.
これが脚本です
ありがとうございます
Thank you.
Mystery
いいないいな　私もほしいです
Gimme, gimme!
Mystery
I wanna see it!
酔っ払い
You're drunk.
I'm fine!
大丈夫ですよ
Show us too, Oreki.
折木　見せて
なるほど　しっかりしてる
I see, it's quite well written.
Yeah, rather detailed.
かなり細かいね
"Be sure not to disturb the tall grass outside the window."
窓の外に足跡などがつかないように
やっぱりちゃんと考えてたのね
So she did consider it after all.
Oh, what about the last person, Sawakiguchi?
それで　次の沢木口さんは？
お待たせー
Sorry to keep you!
チャオ～
Ciao!
こんにちは　沢木口さん
Good afternoon, Sawakiguchi!
チャオです
Ciao to you too!
Oh man, at marketing we're in like, such a bind without the title.
いやー　広報班的にはね　タイトルがないことに困ってるのよ
We can't even finish the posters, you know?
宣伝ポスターの製作も止まっちゃってるし
この辺で脚本にはけりをつけたいところよね
I wanna just see that script over and done with already.
本郷さんは自分から脚本に立候補されたのですか
Did Hongou volunteer to write the script?
いや　他薦だったよ
Nope. Majority vote.
ミステリーにしたのは？
Who decided that it'd be a mystery?
That was a vote, too.
それも多数決
And who decided to make a movie?
そもそも　ビデオ映画になったのは…
なんかずれてきてないか
Aren't we getting a bit off-topic?
でも　私気になります
But I can't stop thinking about it!
はい　議事録あるよ　参考になるなら持ってて
Here's the minutes of our meeting.
Check it out if you think it'll help.
Thank you.
ありがとうございます
All right!
さて　あたしの考えを聞いてもらおうかな
Listen to my theory, 'kay?
I want you guys to think of the word "mystery" and tell me what you see!
君たち　「ミステリー」って言われたら　どんなの想像する？
じゃあ　君
Let's start with... you!
The Orient Express.
「オリエント急行」とか
That's a detective novel! Pretty hardcore.
それじゃ推理小説でしょう？　マニアックね
If you asked for "mystery" in a video rental shop,
レンタルビデオ屋とかで　ミステリーって言ったら
you'd usually get stuff like Friday the 13th or Nightmare on Elm Street.
「十三日の金曜日」とか「エルム街の悪夢」とかでしょう？　普通
But aren't those horror fi—
いや　それじゃホラーでしょう
ああ　確かに
I see, that's right!
Think about it like someone who isn't interested in the genre.
そういうジャンルに全然興味のない普通の人として考えてみなよ
No 31. What should the murder weapon be?
Knife (stabbing) - 10
Rope (strangulation) - 8
Hammer (beating) - 3
Others:
cover with oil and set on fire - 1
push off a high place - 2
Knife suggested (Hongou has final say)
No 32. How many murderers should there be?
1 - 6
2 - 10
3 - 3
More: 4 - 1
Invalid ballot: 1
Everyone dies: 2
About 100: 1
Two persons suggested (Hongou has final say)
For them, mystery and horror are the same.
ミステリーもホラーも区別なんかつかないよ
And nobody like, entered the room that Kaitou died in, right?
それでね　海藤の死んでた部屋には誰も入れなかったんでしょう
だったら　七人目がいるに決まってるじゃない
So there's gotta be a seventh person! It's obvious!
七人目？
A seventh person?
本郷はあの六人の他にもうひとり出演者を探し回ってたのよ
Hongou was looking for a seventh person besides the six actors.
As the characters start to distrust each other more and more,
お互いがお互いを信じられなくなって　みんなの疑心暗鬼が高まったとき
they start seeing a slasher around every corner! And then a real one appears!
満を持して怪人の登場よ
怪人
A slasher?
どれくらい殺す予定だったのかは知らないけど
I dunno how many of them would end up dying.
Probably all of them except one couple.
適当なカップル以外　残りはさくっとやっちゃえばいいんじゃないかな
Then that couple would fend off the killer,
ラストはカップルが怪人を倒して　朝日にキスで決め
Care
and it'd all be over with a kiss lit by the rising sun!
The title could be like,
タイトルは　そうね　「Bloody Beast」とか
"Bloody Beast" or something.
Dunno, I guess that'd be kinda lame?
なんてね　ちょっとかっこ悪いか
But that's something you guys could believe, right?
でも　これならみんな納得よね
B-But what about the room of the murder?
で　でも先輩　密室はどうなるんです？　鍵がかかってたのは
It was locked, after all!
Who cares about a lock or two?
別にいいじゃない　鍵くらい
Horror movie slashers never have any trouble with that stuff.
怪人なんだから　壁抜けくらいできないと
じゃなかったら…
Otherwise... Oh, right! How about a vengeful spirit!
そうだ！　怨霊なのよ！
うん　そっちもありね
That'd work too!
違います　絶対違います
No way! Not a chance!
沢木口さんの案は絶対に本郷さんの本意じゃありません！
Sawakiguchi's theory definitely isn't what Hongou had in mind!
そうだよね　私もどこから冗談なのかわかんなかった
That's right...
I'm still not sure if this is a joke or not.
でも　否定できる？
But can you refute it? Using logic only.
あくまで論理的に
でも　違います
But it's wrong!
That's why I said "using logic".
だからさ　論理的に
違うったら　違うんです
But wrong is wrong!
Chi?
ちぃちゃん？
It's like a kaleidoscope.
万華鏡のようです
Kaleidoscope?
万華鏡？
Hey, Chi!
ちょっ　ちぃちゃん！
ちぃちゃん？
Chi?
She's asleep.
寝ちゃったみたい
それにしても　さっきの沢木口先輩の案
I did like how daring Sawakiguchi's theory was.
あの大胆さはよかったね
Me too, actually.
実は俺も気に入ってる
I thought so.
だろうね
まあ　矛盾はあるけどな
But unfortunately, it's not possible.
何？
What?
You saw how elaborate the script was, right?
脚本の細かさは見ただろう
本郷が後半にああいうホラー展開を考えていたなら
If Hongou wanted it to turn into a horror film halfway through,
she would've at least listed the necessary props.
小道具の手配くらいはやれたはずだ　一番必要な物を
And what does a horror film need most?
What does it need most?
一番必要な物って？
ほら　羽場が「気をきかせたー」とか言う
Come on.
Haba mentioned it too.
本郷の指示した血糊の量はほんのちょっとだった
Hongou only asked for a little bit of blood.
As he tried to awaken
Kaitou, Sugimura
realized his hands
were covered in blood.
The script is also written under that assumption.
脚本の記述もそれを裏付けてる
Which means Hongou wasn't planning some kind of bloodbath.
だから　本郷は大量殺人をやらかすつもりはなかった
なるほど
That's right. It wouldn't be much of a horror movie with only one death.
死者が一人じゃホラーはさびしすぎるね
なんでも理由はつくものなのねえ
Everything has a reason, huh?
いかがでしたか
How was it?
却下です
Not possible.
ちぃちゃん　しっかり
Chi, get a hold of yourself!
すみません
結局全部却下しちゃったね
In the end, we refuted all their theories.
What'll happen to the movie now?
あのビデオ映画　どうなるんだろう
I guess it'll remain incomplete.
まあ　完成は無理だろ
That's a shame.
侘しいね
"That's all that remains of warriors' dreams", huh?
「兵どもが夢の跡」ってところか
Later!
じゃあね
Yeah...
技術のない者がいくら情熱を注いでも　結果は知れたもの
Enthusiasm is no substitute for skill, as you can see here.
少し茶を飲むだけの時間をもらえないかな
Would you join me for tea?
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
Find me, I beg you
まどろみの約束
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
芽生えてた温もり　暖かくて戸惑う
This sprouting warmth confuses us
こんな気持ちをまだ　あなたは分からないよ
Don't you understand this feeling yet?
そんな視線には意味なんて　別にないはず
Normally such random glances hold no meaning
だって友達にしてるのと同じ
Isn't it the same when making friends?
明け方に消えてく　小さな願星
The little shooting stars we wish upon, vanishing into the dawn
夜の間だけの魔法を…
are a magic that only unfolds in the night
今夜恋に変わる　幸せな夢で会おう
Let us meet in a blissful dream tonight, let it be our love
きっと　ねぇ見つけてね
Find me, I beg you
まどろみの約束
We promised to meet, drifting in and out of sleep
次回　万人の死角
Next time: In Everyone's Blind Spot.
In Everyone's Blind Spot